Taft, Philip Papers 5541
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series II. Research/Subject Files
  - Unemployment, 1921-1955 (Box 13, Folder 14a)
    "President Gompers' Report to Meeting of Executive Council, November 14-19, 1921 ... on President's Unemployment Conference ..." 26 pages; form letter and questionnaire for nationwide census on unemployment, from AFL President Green, March 12, 1930; "Unemployment: A Practical Program," booklet by League for Independent Political Action, stamped "received June 10, 1930," 12 pages; memo to President Green from AFL legislative representative W. C. Roberts, suggesting he sign attached form letter to all members at the House, objecting to statement that AFL supported certain unemployment legislation, June 26, 1930; Two from letters re part-time employment survey, August 27 and September 24, 1930; five "Unemployment Report[s] of the AFL," showing unemployment rates in major cities, by trade with percentage increase/decrease over previous month April 1930-31; minutes of AFL Executive Council, opposing wage cutting, May 13, 1931; calling for establishment of relief agencies, August 12, 1931; letter from AFL President Green to Chairman, Committee on Unemployment Relief, suggesting that available work be divided up evenly among all working people, so that all might be employed, September 22, 1931, 3 pages; memo for President Green from AFL representative W. C. Hushing, reporting on meeting of President's Committee [on Unemployment Plans and Suggestions] re public works projects for unemployment relief, survey of 25 economists, consensus that "large appropriations by the Federal Government for immediate use would be futile," December 2, 1931; telegrams between President Green and AFL official re bills for federal public works appropriations, December 28, 1931; minutes of the AFL Executive Council calling for shorter work hours, July 20, 1932; "Recommendations Submitted by the Representatives of the American Federation of Labor and Railroad Brotherhoods," March 30, 1933, 4 pages; memo for President Green re complaints about 5/hr., 10 hr./day work-relief wages, June 28, 1933; resolution adopted at AFL convention, urging increased public work relief, January 25, 1937; memo for President Green from AFL legislative representative W. C. Hushing, reiterating request for definition of policy on Relief Bill; reply noted, May 17, 1937; "Confidential" memo for files re Administration proposal for annual wage for building tradesmen, AFL opposition, November 24, 1937; "Statement Upon the Business and Economic Conditions of the Nation Issued by the Executive Council of the AFL," calling on government and private industry to cooperate in relieving unemployment, February 14, 1939; "Memorandum for Mr. Green" from AFL legislative representative W. C. Roberts re Work Relief Bill and opposition in House to Amendment for prevailing wage, July 11, 1939; "Statement by William Green, President, AFL, In Support of Senate Bill 1274, Submitted to the Committee on Finance, U.S. Senate," supporting amendment to War Mobilization and Reconversion Act of 1944 providing supplementary unemployment compensation, August 29, 1945, 14 pages; minutes of AFL Executive Council re unemployment May 10, 1950; "On the Economic Outlook," May 13, 1954; "Statement by the Executive Council of the AFL: The Economic Situation" February 1, 1955 and August 9, 1955; notes.
  - Unions - Expulsions, Suspensions, Fines, 1900-1955 (Box 13, Folder 15-16)
  - Unions - Free Speech - Notes, 1898-1954 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Unions - Miscellaneous - Notes (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - United Hebrew Trades, 1915-1918 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - United Labor Policy Committee, 1950-1951 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    Manu minutes of meetings, 1951; "Union Representatives in Government Agencies," a report on labor participation in defense agencies since last spring, indicating problems and accomplishments, December 19, 1951; "Equal Sacrifice for the Defense of America," report of the United Labor Conference, March 21, 1951; Statements and press releases by Committee: (announcing the establishment of the Committee, December 15, 1951; to the National Wage Stabilization Board, January 11, 1951, 20 pages; announcing resignation of all labor representatives from defense mobilization agencies in protest of wage and price controls, February 28, 1951, 5 pages; announcing the return of all labor representatives to the defense mobilization agencies due to changes in government policy, April 30, 1951, 3 pages; by CIO President Murray on United Labor Policy Committee, regretting withdrawal of AFL, August 28, 1951, 2 pages; correspondence between Director, Defense Mobilization Committee and United Labor Policy Committee, January 19 and February 20, 1951; statement of cash receipts and expenditures, May 26, 1951 to October 15, 1951, inclusive; notes.
  - United Nations, 1945-1953 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    American Federation of Labor Views and Suggestions to the San Francisco Conference for Amending the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals, May 2, 1945, 7 pages; minutes of AFL Executive Council meeting re Dumbarton Oaks conference, May 8, 1945; memorandum to AFL Executives Woll and Dubinsky from AFL U.N. representative re difficulties of passing a U.N. resolution against forced labor, 1948, 3 pages; letter to U.S. Secretary of State from AFL Executive Matthew Woll protesting U.S. delegates action on U.N. Economic and Social Council re forced labor issue, March 2, 1948; "Report on Activities of the AFL's Consultants in the U.N." May 12, 1949, 6 pages (with original signatures of Matthew Woll and David Dubinsky); "Statement by George P. Delaney, International Representative, AFL, before the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations," February 9, 1950 re Soviet genocide, supporting proposed U.N. genocide convention, 6 pages; letter to U.N. Secretary General Dag Hammarskjold from AFL Vice-President Matthew Woll re Soviet indoctrination of P.O.W.'s, forced repatriation in Korean Armistice, September 30, 1953; notes
  - Unskilled Workers - Organized by AFL, 1900-1933 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Diamond Jubilee Anniversary issue, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    notes
  - Upholsterers, 1936-1956 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Utility Workers, 1934-1935 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Veterans Affairs, 1945-1952 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    Recommendations by AFL representatives to Congressional and government advisory committees in support of various retraining programs, 1945-52; notes
  - Wage Stabilization Board, 1946-1952 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    "Dissenting Opinion of Labor Members of Wage Stabilization Board Concerning Regulation No. 6," 13 pages, c. 1950-51; "Summary of Arguments Against Adoption of the Dirkson Amendment (Reorganizing the Wage Stabilization Board) by the Banking and Currency Committee," c. 1952, 3 pages; "Summary of the Wage Stabilization Board Policies Governing Health and Welfare Plans," prepared for the Research Council for Economic Security, January 1952; "Research Report - AFL - The Wage Stabilization Situation," May-June 1951; Building and Construction Trades Bulletin: "The Wage Freeze," February 1951; "Remarks of George D. Riley, Member, National Legislative Committee, AFL, Before the Lucas Subcommittee of the House Committee of Education and Labor," June 15, 1951, 3 pages; "Statement of Joseph Keenan, representing the AFL, at a Wage Stabilization Board Hearing on Contractual Agreements Providing for Deferred Wage Increases," May 24, 1951, 4 pages; "Statement of Walter J. Mason, Member, National Legislative Committee AFL Before the Subcommittee on Labor and Labor-Management Relations of the Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare," May 31, 1951, 8 pages; "Disputes and Wage Stabilization Functions," 4 page unsigned transcript of address, apparently by legislator, May 27, 1952; "Statement of President Green in Respect to S 2594 (the Maybank Bill)," opposing, June 5, 1952, 6 pages; "Statement of Walter J. Mason, ... AFL ... Before the House Education and Labor Committee on Investigation of the National Wage Stabilization Board," 14 pages; "Why I Am Opposed to Sec. 106 of the Amendments to the Defense Production Act (the Dirksen-Bricker Amendment)," unsigned 3 page manuscript, probably by legislator, n.d.; notes.
  - Wages and Hours, 1880-1938 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    Letter to chairman, House Appropriation Committee from Secretary, AFL, opposing Economy Act and 11 percent wage cut, December 9, 1932, 4 pages with attached resolution; memo for AFL President Green re status of minimum wage legislation in states, 4 pages, January 29, 1934; Conference Board Service Letter, publication of the National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., with chart re "Wages and the Cost of Living," February 28, 1935; press release by AFL Metal Trades and Building Trades Departments urging Black-Connery minimum wage bill to be referred back to committee, July 30, 1937, with attached memo from AFL legislative representative to Building and Construction Trades Department, recommending support for bill, May 13, 1936; "Minutes of Meeting on Wages and Hours Conference ... November 20, 1937, In Mr. Green's Office," 4 pages; memo to President Green from AFL legislative representative re enforcement of minimum wage rates, November 22, 1937; Letter to House Labor Committee Chair Mary Norton from AFL President Green stating AFL position on Fair Labor Standards Bill, November 22, 1937, 4 pages; Draft of press release re above communication, 4 pages; letter to Senator Walsh and Representative Healey, authors of the Walsh-Healey Government Purchase Act, from President, Boot and Shoe Workers' Union, urging establishment of minimum wage for shoe manufacturers under government contract, November 30, 1937, 2 pages; "Analysis of S 2475," unsigned, December 1937, 8 pages; letter to U.S. legislator from AFL legislative representative clarifying AFL position on wage and hour legislation, December 15, 1937, 3 pages; letter to Secretary-Treasurer, Oklahoma Trades and Labor Council stating AFL support of uniform minimum wage and maximum hour legislation, February 23, 1938; letter to House Labor Committee Chair Mary Norton from AFL President Green stating "unalterable opposition" to S 2475, the Wages and Hours Bill, April 11, 1938, 5 pages; report to AFL President Green from AFL Counsel Padway, analyzing proposed Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938 and comparing with proposed AFL wage and hour bill, April 13, 1938, 4 pages; memo for President Green from AFL legislative representative re amendments to Government Contract Act (Walsh-Healey Act) with full text of amendments attached, May 9, 1938; letter to President Green from President, International Printing Pressman and Assistants' Union of North America, warning that federal establishment of minimum wage will lower wages in many cases, becoming the maximum wage, and discourage unionization, May 16, 1938, and reply, may 19, 1938; similar letter to Secretary, International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers Local 100, May 25, 1938; memos from AFL legislative representative re appointment of conferences on Wage and Hour Bill, May 31, 1938; re "AFL Policy Toward Congressmen Who Vote Against Wage and Hour Bill--Particularly, Senator Connally," June 1, 1938; "Statement by Attorney Thatcher in reference to telegram from Judge Padway" re proposed amendment to Walsh-Healy Act and potential damage to AFL vis--vis CIO, June 4, 1938, 3 pages; memorandum for file re Wage and Hour Bill, likelihood of support by various members of Congress, particularly House Labor Committee Chair Mary Norton, June 8, 1938; form letters; notes.
  - Wages and Hours, 1948-1966 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    "Statement by William Green, President, AFL, Before Senate Committee on Banking and Currency on Anti-Inflation Legislation, January 22, 1948," 8 pages plus 4 pages of charts; "Statement Presented by [AFL representative] Before the Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare on the Fair Labor Standards Act, April 20, 1948," calling for improvements, i.e. higher minimum wage, broader occupational coverage, child labor coverage, 8 pages plus 9 pages of appendices; "Statement Presented by [AFL representative] Before House Committee on Education and Labor on Revision of Fair Labor Standards Act, February 1, 1949," 8 pages plus 4; minutes of the AFL Executive Council, recommending economic measures in light of outbreak of Korean War: wage and price controls, increased taxes, rationing, August 8-11, 1950; "Statement by the Executive Council, AFL," against abolition of price controls, criticizing Congress, May 19, 1952; copy of Labor Relations Reporter special issue: "The Fair Labor Standards Act Amendments of 1966" with explanation of changes and text of act as amended by Bureau of National Affairs, Inc.; notes.
  - Waterfront Employers - Briefs, 1940-1948 (Box 13, Folder 29-31)
  - Web Weavers Unions, 1888 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Women - Minimum Wage, Equal Opportunity, 1898-1935 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    "Employed Women Under N.R.A. Codes," bulletin of the U.S. Department of Labor, Women's Bureau, 1935; notes
  - Work Stoppages, 1955-1971 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Bureau of Labor Statistics reports re work stoppages: "Basic Steel Industry, 1901-60", Government Employees, 1942-61", "Bituminous-Coal Mining Industry, 1927-54"; "Report to the President - The Labor Dispute in the Bituminous Coal Industry" submitted by the Board of Inquiry Under Executive Order 10106, February 11, 1950; "An Analysis of West Virginia Work Stoppages," Institute for Labor Studies, West Virginia University, 1971
  - Work Stoppages, 1881-1963 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Workers Education, 1921-1963 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    "An American Adventure in Workers' Education" by Charles A. Beard, and "The Workers' Education Bureau - An Arm of the Labor Movement," by Fannia M. Cohn, reprinted from Workers' Education, 15th Anniversary Issue, October 1936; "Vocational Education and Federal Policy" by the Upjohn Institute for Employment Research, May 1963; notes.
  - Workers' Rights, 1925-1953 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Letter from AFL President Gompers to individual, against suggestion to limit freedom of the press by constitutional amendment, February 20, 1925; "Free Speech, Free Press for Civil Service Employees," n.d., unsigned, apparently report by AFL legislative representative; "Memo for Mr. Green" re garnishment and attachment of wages, state-by-state legislation, January 29, 1934; "Memorandum for Mr. Roberts [AFL legislative representative]" re lobbying efforts with Senator LaFollette re resolution providing for investigations for violations of rights of free speech/ assembly and of labor unions to bargain collectively, March 27, 1936; "Loyalty and Private Employment: The Right of Employers to Discharge Suspected Subversives," reprinted from the Yale Law Journal, Volume 62, Number 6, May, 1953; notes.
  - Works Project Administration (WPA), 1938-1939 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    Correspondence between President, United Garment Workers, AFL President Green, AFL legislative representative W. C. Roberts and Director, WPA Section of Labor Relations re effect of WPA sewing project on regular garment workers, with suggestion that WPA workers not be taught skills on modern equipment, June-August 1938; letter to Chairman, Senate Subcommittee on Defense Appropriations, from Secretary -Treasurers of AFL Building and Construction Trades and Metal Trades Departments re AFL opposition to amendment lowering wage rates under WPA, January 18, 1939; "Report of Special Committee to the Conference of Representatives of National and International Unions on the WPA Situation" re strikes in WPA jobs following wage reductions, calling for maintenance of "prevailing wage" provisions, July 12, 1939, 5 pages; form letters; notes.
  - World War I - Committee on Labor, 1916-1919 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    Letter from Secretary of War, informing AFL President Gompers of his appointment as member of Advisory Commission to Council of National Defense, October 30, 1916 and reply from Gompers, accepting, October 31, 1916; "Advisory Commission, Council of National Defense. The Labor Committee. Plan of Administration," detailing Gompers' powers as Chairman, procedures in his absence, 9 pages, n.d.; one page statement of purpose of Labor Committee, n.d.; "Invitation for Membership on Committee on Labor," 8 page list of union officials, with 2 form letters by Gompers, inviting membership, March 22, 1917; list of Labor Committee Executive Committee members; form letter from Gompers to AFL union officials re labor conference, importance of maintaining labor's voice in national emergency measures, March 2, 1917, 4 pages; minutes of the Committee on Labor re groups represented on the Committee, April 2, 1917, 3 pages; annual report of Labor Committee re visiting labor delegation from England, policy that wages and working conditions should not be lowered during the war, with detailed committee recommendations re sanitation, housing, etc., policy re women in industry, industrial training, military dependents, 1917, 52 pages; "Resolution Adopted at Meeting of Executive Committee, Labor Committee - Conservation of Health and Welfare of Workers," April 5, 1917, "Amplification" of above to correct public misinterpretation, April 16, 1917; letter from Gompers to Teamsters President Daniel Tobin, clarifying position re striking, April 17, 1917; letter from Gompers to Chairman, Council of National Defense, re attempts to lower standards of working conditions, April 26, 1917; letter from Gompers to members of Labor Committee, asking them to come to a meeting with British delegates, May 9, 1917; Gompers' remarks at the meeting of the Labor Committee, May 15, 1917, 17 pages; statement of United Mine Workers, unsigned, protesting policy of Committee on Coal Production and lack of mine worker representation on the committee, May 21, 1917, 4 pages; letter to Gompers from the Metal Polishers, Platers, Brass and Silver Workers Union, asking for investigation of increase in hours, without compensation, at Remington gun plant, May 24, 1917; letter from Gompers to Advisory Commission, Council of National Defense re resolution by Executive Committee, Committee on Labor, urging government adoption of safety standards for government suppliers during the war, June 8, 1917; letter from Gompers to Bernard Baruch, Advisory Commission of Council of National Defense, nominating various union officials for Council committees, June 16, 1917; letter, unsigned, probably from Gompers, from Labor Committee to Chairman, Advisory Committee re resolution for establishment of War Labor Board, August 27, 1917; letter to Gompers from Director, Council of National Defense, excerpting minutes of meeting between Council and Advisory Commission re conditions and procedures for suspension of labor laws in individual factories due to declared "war emergency", December 4, 1917; material re attempt to exempt farmers from draft, noting opposition by Labor Committee, October 1917; remarks of Gompers at Joint Meeting of the Council of National Defense and the Advisory Committee re slowness in implementing recommendations on housing and wages, and re allegations that Labor is unpatriotic, February 7, 1918, 7 pages; letter from Gompers to President Woodrow Wilson, urging that the Council of National Defense be continued after the war to assist in National readjustment and beyond, November 27, 1918, and reply from Wilson, in general agreement, November 27, 1918; letter from Gompers to AFL Executive Council re representation at the Presidential Industrial Conference, September 26, 1919, 3 pages; notes.
  - World War I - Defense, 1916-1918 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Resolution for creation of National Board of Labor Adjustment, sent to Gompers for approval, April 24, 1917; brochure "American Labor's Position In Peace or In War," March 12, 1917; flyer by International Association of Machinists, "A Protest Against Gompers," denouncing Gompers' assistance in war effort, n.d.; memoranda of understanding between Gompers, Secretary of War and Secretary of Navy re military construction and wages and hours, June-July 1917; letters between President, United Brotherhood of Leatherworkers and Secretary of War official Walter Lippman re policy of not changing existing contract conditions on government projects, August 3, 1917; letter to President, Building Trades Council, St. Louis, Missouri from ex- employee of construction company, who quit due to bad conditions, with description of conditions, August 3, 1917; letter from Gompers to Cantonment Adjustment Board, protesting conditions at construction projects in Puerto Rico, warning of damage to U.S. credibility internationally, May 6, 1918; notes.
  - World War I - Peace, 1918-1919 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    Correspondence between Gompers and American Commission to Negotiate Peace, thanking Gompers for work on Commission, September-October 1919; notes.
  - World War I - War Labor Policies Board, 1918 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    Memorandum re appointment of Felix Frankfurter to head Board with list of other appointments, May 23, 1918; notes.
  - World War II - Defense, 1936-1942 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    Minutes of AFL Executive Council endorsing statements re necessity to uphold labor standards in defense production, May 5-8, 1940; similar minutes, February 19, 1941; copy of letter "which was never sent" (pencil notation) from AFL President Green to President Roosevelt calling for labor participation in defense production plans, May 17, 1940; "Metal Trades Department, AF of L," report of national conference re apprenticeship training, calling for placement of unemployed skilled metalworkers as first priority, June 20, 1940, 3 pages; letter to Secretary of Labor Perkins outlining proposals for defense mobilization from AFL officials Frank Fenton and Robert Watt, August 15, 1940, 5 pages; "Monthly Survey of Business of the AFL," September- November 1940, with "Wage increases recently reported by Affiliated Unions"; report of national conference of Building and Construction Trades Department, noting number of skilled workers, satisfaction of military and other government agencies with building trades contribution to defense mobilization, January 7, 1941, 2 pages; nine page list of labor advisors on various government defense related agencies, pencil notation "7/30/41",; "Defense" statement from AFL Weekly News Service, May 29, 1941, 3 pages; "New Planning Board Named On Defense Production," from Congressional Daily, February 21, 1941; press release announcing Executive Order establishing National Defense Mediation Board, with list of membership, March 19, 1941, 3 pages; Labor's Monthly Survey, "Wage Policy In Defense" and "Labor Prepares for Great Defense Effort," April and May 1941, by AFL, with comparisons of productivity, wages, profits, and cost of living ("wages should not be tied to cost of living") between the two World Wars; memorandum to AFL President Green from AFL legislative representative W. C. Hushing re demand of Senate Special Sub-Committee on National Defense that Green appear to make statement on West Coast shipyard strike, May 23, 1941; letter from Green to AFL legislative representative Robert Watt re creation of AFL Committee for National Defense with list of membership and outline of problems for consideration, 7 pages; letter to AFL Vice-President Matthew Woll, as Chairman of the Defense Committee, from Committee Assistant Secretary Florence Thorne re discussion agenda with President Green, July 17, 1941
  - World War II - Defense, 1936-1942 (Box 14, Folder 12cont.)